Okay בוקר טוב boker tov today's דף daf is קלג kuf lamed
gimmel 133, we're a little bit behind, we're an עמוד amud behind.
We picked up on the top of קלב עמוד ב kuf lamed
bet amud bet and מכלל כתובות שנו כאן, miklal ketuvot shanu kan,
maybe just for context we'll read again from the bottom of קלב
עמוד א, kuf lamed bet amud alef, and we're quoting a משנה
mishnah in פאה pe'ah and the reason we're quoting these various having
these various discussions here is because רבא Rava is going to ask
on all of them. All of them are in the context of
a שכיב מרע, shchiv mirah, somebody who's on his deathbed and רבא
Rava is going to ask whether the same thing applies also to
somebody who is not on his deathbed. So here's what the משנה
mishnah says in פאה. pe'ah. הכותב נכסיו לבניו וכתב לאשתו קרקע כל
שהוא איבדה כתובתה. hakotev nechasav levanav vechatav leishto karka kol shehu ibdah
ketuvatah.
If somebody was basically distributing his property to his children on his
deathbed and maybe not just verbally in writing, but he also gave
his woman his wife a little piece of property, then she loses
her כתובה. ketuvah. Now what does that mean she loses her כתובה?
ketuvah? So probably the simplest read, which is that of the ר"י
מיגש, Ri Megash, but the רשב"ם Rashbam rejects this, the simplest read
is that that's treated as total payment of her כתובה. ketuvah. She's
owed 200 זוז, zuz, I don't know, call it $10,000, this little
piece of land is worth $100, but the fact that it's clear
that the husband that the husband is distributing the father's distributing all
of his property, so you know if he's redistributing to his kids
they're not going to get the normal inheritance they're going to get
based on the will then he's also giving her the piece of
property he's giving her it should be understood in payment of the
כתובה. ketuvah.
That's one read. Let's read it that way and then we'll go
into say how the רשב"ם Rashbam reads it. Okay, so now the
גמרא gemara challenges this. משום דכתב לה קרקע כל שהוא איבדה כתובתה?
mishum dechatav lah karka kol shehu ibdah ketuvatah? Just because he wrote
off, you know, he gave her a little piece of property would
we say she loses her כתובה? ketuvah? If the guy owed some
external debtor, you know, $10,000
and he was distributing his property on his deathbed and he gave
this person a little piece of property we wouldn't say that's in
payment of the $10,000. Maybe it's a partial payment, that's $100, but
the rest of the debt he's going to collect he has liens
on the estate. So the wife also should be able to collect
the rest of her כתובה ketuvah from the property that the children
have received. So the גמרא gemara says אמר רב במזכה להן על
ידה. amar Rav bemezakeh lahen al yadah. So everybody's trying to explain
that it's a case where we can a little bit more see
her willingness and that she's understanding this is meant to be in
payment of her כתובה ketuvah and she's going along with it. So
רב Rav says that she's participating in the קנין. kinyan. She gives
the husband a handkerchief and he takes it and through that all
of the property is distributed to the to the sons and to
her. So the fact that she's actively participating in it going to
the sons is showing that she's sort of saying like okay they
can keep what they have and I'll take what you're giving me
and I'm not going to go ahead and demand my כתובה, ketuvah,
you know, from their estate from what they have. ושמואל אמר במחלק
לפניה והיא שתקה. uShmuel amar bemechallek lefaneha vehia shatkah. No, even if
she's not actively participating he's just distributing it to the sons, she's
in the presence, she's not saying well what about my כתובה, ketuvah,
where am I going to collect my כתובה ketuvah from? So then
it's understood that she's okay they get what's theirs and she's waiving
her rights and she's taking what little is given to her. ורבי
יוסי בר חנינא אומר באומר לה טלי קרקע זה בכתובתך. veRabbi Yosi
bar Chanina omer beomer lah tali karka zeh beketuvateich. Maybe this is
the one that makes the most sense, although the רשב"ם Rashbam says
that this is the biggest חידוש chiddush and where he explicitly says
this little piece of property is for your כתובה. ketuvah. Now, I
mean he says it's for your כתובה ketuvah and she agrees, shouldn't
that be just a normal פסק? psak? But maybe the point is
that we would normally read it as maybe it's a maybe it
is, you know, a partial payment towards your כתובה. ketuvah. Why are
we interpreting it to be the entire payment of the כתובה? ketuvah?
Or maybe again maybe she's just doing it because she doesn't want
to upset her husband who's on the deathbed. Okay, but we don't
say any of that, we treat it as she has fully gotten
her כתובה ketuvah paid off, she is waiving her rights to collect
the rest from what the sons have. ומכלל כתובות שנו כאן, umiklal
ketuvot shanu kan, now the top of קלב עמוד ב, kuf lamed
bet amud bet, ומכלל כתובות שנו כאן, umiklal ketuvot shanu kan, and
this is really the גמרא gemara concedes, leniencies of the כתובה. ketuvah.
I mean it's lenient to the husband or to the children, but
it's understood you know it's a little ironic the כתובה ketuvah is
there to protect the interests of the wife, but also the גמרא
gemara was dealing with a socio-economic reality that husbands could not have,
well potential husbands, too big of barriers before getting married, so there
had to be certain ways in which, you know, the husband's interests
were being attended to as well. So that's at least how the
גמרא gemara initially positions it. I should say that what you know
this idea that I said the full כתובה ketuvah is paid that's
the way the ר"י מיגש Ri Megash read it. The רשב"ם Rashbam
reads it, no, she's waiving she's accepting whatever little piece of property
she's accepting in exchange for waiving her liens on the estate as
it exists and what the children are inheriting. But she waived her
liens but the debt still exists. So if the husband inherits more
property between now and when he dies then that she still has
the debt still exists she has just accepted this piece of property
and foregone the liens on the current estate. That's the way the
רשב"ם Rashbam understands it. Anyway, now the גמרא gemara is going to
see whether this is the right understanding of that משנה. mishnah. תנן.
tnan. So we taught in the משנה, Mishna, this is actually the
end of the משנה. Mishna. רבי יוסי אומר אם קיבלה עליה אף
על פי שלא כתב לה איבדה כתובתה. Rabbi Yose omer im kibla
aleha af al pi shelo katav la ibda ketuvata. If she explicitly
accepted upon herself that she's waiving her rights, waiving the debt, accepting
this as total payment of the debt, then he says, then, you
know, then even without distributing the property, she forfeits her כתובה. ketuvah.
Now that seems to be pretty clear that like you need if
she explicitly did it, that should be okay. But the גמרא Gemara
wants to understand is רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose being more lenient or
being more strict than the תנא קמא. tanna kamma. So let's see
what the גמרא Gemara
says. איבדה כתובתה. ibda ketuvata. So the גמרא Gemara says מכלל דתנא
קמא סבר כתיבה וקבלה בעי. michlal detanna kamma sivar ksiva vekabala ba'ei.
It sounds like the תנא קמא tanna kamma says you need both.
You need him both to distribute the property, which is what, you
know, the משנה Mishna said, plus she needs to explicitly say, I
accept this as payment of my כתובה, ketuvah, I am waiving my
rights. And רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is saying, no, accepting is enough
without distributing the property. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says,
one minute. וכי תימא כולה רבי יוסי. vechi teima kulah Rabbi Yose.
Maybe the
beginning and
the end are two, are like the two sides
of the coin and they're both רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. So meaning
that the first position is saying that כתיבה ksiva suffices and then
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is saying and also קבלה kabala without כתיבה
ksiva suffices. That would be a way to read it although there's
no way to read רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose as more strict. But
what you could read is that the first position is כתיבה ksiva
is enough and then רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is saying not only
is כתיבה ksiva enough, קבלה kabala without כתיבה ksiva is also enough.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, that doesn't sound like what's going
on in the משנה. Mishna. We have a ברייתא braisa that explains
that the תנא קמא tanna kamma genuinely is being more strict. I
don't know if strict is the right word, but anyway genuine demanding
more before she loses her
rights. והתניא, vehatanya, we taught a ברייתא. braisa. אמר רבי יהודה, amar
Rabbi Yehuda, said רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, אימתי, eimasai, when is this
true? And when רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says אימתי eimasai he's coming
to not disagree but to clarify. When is the תנא קמא tanna
kamma saying that the woman, the wife loses her rights to the
כתובה? ketuvah? שהיתה שם וקיבלה עליה. shehayesa sham vekibla aleha. She was
there and she accepted. So both some of the qualifications, you know,
the גמרא Gemara said, there was בפניה, befaneha, etc., but also explicitly
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is clarifying the תנא קמא tanna kamma needs
both. She was there when he was distributing it and she explicitly
agreed to lose, that that would be in payment of the כתובה.
ketuvah. אבל היתה שם ולא קיבלה עליה, קיבלה עליה ולא היתה שם,
aval hayesa sham velo kibla aleha, kibla aleha velo hayesa sham, one
or without the other, being there without explicitly accepting, explicitly accepting without
being there when it was being distributed לא איבדה כתובתה lo ibda
ketuvata she did not lose it. And comes along רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says no, accepting suffices. Okay, so
now that seems to be a good read of the משנה. Mishna.
תנא קמא tanna kamma says you need both. Now why do you
need both? If she was just there when he distributed, fine. Why
should we say she's forfeiting her כתובה? ketuvah? But if she explicitly
said, I accept, you know, payment of my כתובה, ketuvah, that this
is in payment of my כתובה, ketuvah, I'm waiving my rights, why
isn't that enough? So presumably because we're actually now being more protective
of the woman. Even if she's explicitly being מוחל, mochel, and normally
what else, what else should you need, because maybe she's doing it
just to make her husband happy, we're not going to treat her
מחילה mechila as a מחילה. mechila. And רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is
coming and saying that actually if she explicitly accepts, that suffices. So
it's a complete reversal of what we said before. It's not that
we treat some silence as if she's accepting it or being nice
to the husband or like whatever, where, you know, she's losing out
on her כתובה ketuvah rights, actually according to the תנא קמא, tanna
kamma, she even if she explicitly accepts she doesn't lose out unless
she is present during this distribution as well and רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says an explicit acceptance will suffice. So the גמרא Gemara says
תיובתא דכולהו תיובתא. tyufta dechulehu tyufta.
That is an absolute refutation of what the earlier אמוראים amoraim said
to explain the משנה. Mishna. It is not, that's right, to sort
of say only in very, you know, create the special circumstances. Here
we see that's not what the תנא קמא tanna kamma was talking
about at all. The תנא קמא tanna kamma required both, and if
she required explicitly קיבלה עליה, kibla aleha, you don't need all of
their explanations of what, you know, of that case to make it
maybe somewhat more understandable.
Okay, so fine. אמר ליה רבא לרב נחמן, amar lei Rava le-Rav
Nachman, so רבא Rava said to רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, הא רב,
הא שמואל, הא רבי יוסי בר חנינא, ha Rav, ha Shmuel, ha
Rabbi Yose bar Chanina, so we have רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel
and רבי יוסי בר חנינא. Rabbi Yose bar Chanina. all explained the
case in different ways, you know, she actively participated, she was there,
etc. So מר מאי סבירא ליה? Mar Mai Sveira Lei? What do
you hold? Now that's a bizarre question because we just refuted all
of them, why is he asking? So what the רשב"ם Rashbam says
is, and we're going to see because he actually holds—well, let's see
what the answer is and then we'll understand. But right now at
the face of it, the question doesn't make sense because the גמרא
Gemara just refuted all of those interpretations of the משנה. Mishnah. So
the גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה, Amar Lei, so he said back,
רב נחמן Rav Nachman said back to רבא, Rava, שאני אומר, She'ani
Omer, I say כיון שעשה שותף בין הבנים איבדה כתובתה. Keivan She'asa
Shutaf Bein HaBanim Ibda Kesuvasa. Once he made her a, you know,
a partner with the children, she lost her כתובה. Kesuvah. Now what
exactly that means made her a partner, that sounds like just describing
the משנה. Mishnah. Does that mean she actively participated? Does that mean
it was in her presence? Not exactly clear. Okay. But it basically
just goes—sounds like the first case of the משנה. Mishnah. So what
does that—how does that work? We just rejected that. We said according
to the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma you need both. So the רשב"ם
Rashbam says he's פוסק Paskening like רבי יוסי. Rebbe Yosi. And we're
going to assume that when רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi says, you know,
קבלה's Kibla enough, רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi also says כתב Kesav is
enough. Which is, again, a little bit of a pretty big assumption.
Okay. So we've now said the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma needs both.
Maybe you could read the question is: when you need the other
thing plus קבלה לה, Kibla Lah, what are its parameters? But that's
not what it sounds like. It sounds like רב נחמן Rav Nachman
is saying, you know, כתב Kesav is enough, שותף בין הבנים Shutaf
Bein HaBanim is enough. So where does that fit in? So again,
רשב"ם Rashbam will say that the same way רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi
says קבלה's Kibla enough, he would say שותף בין הבנים Shutaf Bein
HaBanim is enough either. רבי יוסי's Rebbe Yosi the one that says
either, תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says both. Okay.
Now, if you take a look at the רשב"ם Rashbam about six
lines down in the wide lines, שותף בין הבנים שכתב לה נמי
קרקע כל שהוא מחלה לה ולא מצריכין לכל הני כוחו דאמרינן לעיל.
Shutaf Bein HaBanim Shekasav Lah Nami Karka Kol Shehu Machla Lah Velo
Matzrichin Lekol Hanei Kocho De'amrinan Le'eil.
You don't need any of the special context. You don't need her
to actively participate. You don't need her to be there. You don't
need her to, you know, to
be—you don't need him to say תלי קרקע זה בכתובתך. Tli Karka
Zeh Bekesuvaseich. Okay.
I mean, so really that's a very big קולא Kula going like
רבי יוסי. Rebbe Yosi. You don't need קבלה Kibla even—even מחלק קרקע—even,
Mechaleik Karka you know, מחלק קרקע Mechaleik Karka is enough. שותף בין
הבנים Shutaf Bein HaBanim is enough. And you don't even need plus
the other special criteria that those other אמוראים Amoraim were adding. Okay.
So let's take a look. איתמר נמי Itmar Nami is also said,
אמר רב יוסף בר מניומי אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Yosef Bar
Minyumi Amar Rav Nachman, again in the name of רב נחמן, Rav
Nachman, כיון שעשה שותף בין הבנים איבדה כתובתה, Keivan She'asa Shutaf Bein
HaBanim Ibda Kesuvasa, like the simple sense of the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma without any special qualifications. בעי רבא, Ba'ei Rava, now this is
the reason we're quoting it, בברי היכי? BeVari Heichi? What would be
the הלכה Halacha if the guy wasn't on his deathbed? Would we
say the same thing and he was distributing his property that the
wife would lose it? מי אמרינן בשכיב מרע הוא דידעה דלית ליה
וכמחלה? Mi Amrinan BeShchiv Meira Hu DeYada DeLeis Lei U'keMachla? By a
שכיב מרע Shchiv Meira she knows he's distributing all the property he
has, that's the case, all the property. She knows he's not going
to get more. It's clear he's basically trying to divest himself of
his estate. So in that case if she's silent and she's accepting,
then that's read as a—giving—accepting that that's what she's going to get.
Okay. That's when we would read it, when it's clearly the divesting
of the whole estate. אבל בברי, Aval BeVari, but if it's a
healthy person and even if he's distributing all of his assets, קסברה
Kasavra she maybe holds הדר קני. Hadar Kani. He sells all of
his assets, he's a young guy, he's in his 30s, whatever, now
he wants to distribute the property he has and he's going to
get more property. So just because I'm accepting this little plot of
land, I'm not accepting it as my entire payment for my כתובה.
Kesuvah. I don't think this is the end of the story. He
wants to give me a little plot of land as a gift
or as a piece of my כתובה, Kesuvah, fine. But why should
I assume this is the end of the story? I'm not implicitly
being מוחל Mochel anything. או דילמא השתא מיהא לית ליה? O Dilma
Hashta Miha Leis Lei? Or do we say no, right now he's,
you know, giving up all of his estate, and she under—you know,
we can assume that she will understand that it's his intent just
to say, "This is it." You know, and therefore if she's willing
to accept it, that is read as a waiving of her כתובה
Kesuvah rights. So the גמרא Gemara says תיקו, Teiku, we don't know.
All right, which is interesting, what would be the הלכה למעשה? Halacha
LeMa'aseh? Probably המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi MeChaveiro Alav HaRa'aya. All right.
ההוא דאמר להו, Hahu De'amar Lehu, a man said to his children,
two daughters, פלגא לברתא פלגא לברתא. Palga LeBarta Palga LeBarta. He had
two daughters, half to one daughter, half to the other daughter, it's
like King Lear. Okay. ותילתא לאיתתא
בפירי. VeSilsa Le'itata BePeiri. And my wife gets a third of the
fruit. And we're assuming for now that the fruit was attached to
the trees. All right. So that would seem to be an exact
case of distributing all the property, the wife gets a little bit.
If we're going to assume that that's enough without explicitly קבלה לה,
Kibla Lah, then this should suffice.
So איקלע רב נחמן לסורא. Iklah Rav Nachman LeSura. רב נחמן Rav
Nachman happened to be in סורא. Sura. ולגבי רב חסדא, U'lgabei Rav
Chisda, and he came to רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. אמר ליה כי
האי גוונא מאי? Amar Lei Ki Hai Gavna Mai? What's the הלכה?
Halacha? Will this work? So what should be the question?
אמר ליה הכי אמר שמואל Amar Lei Hachi Amar Shmuel one who
explained the משנה mishna originally and we seem to have rejected שמואל.
Shmuel. But somehow even though the גמרא Gemara seems to have rejected
it, we're back to understanding that the simple sense of the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma without the רב יהודה Reb Yehuda without all of
that, simply giving the wife a little bit, she loses her כתובה
ketubah when it's all being distributed. And שמואל Shmuel said, even if
it's only
a דקל אחד לפירותיו, dekel echad l'peirotav, אבדה כתובתה. ivda ketubatah. Because
here's the question, right? What's the שאלה? shayla? Isn't this exactly the
case of the משנה mishna the way we're reading it now? But
fruit is not the land itself. It's מחובר לקרקע, mechubar l'karka, it's
attached to the tree that's attached to the ground, but it's not
a piece of land itself. So if it's important that it's divesting
of the land and that's really seen as the primary estate and
that's when it's אבדה כתובתה, ivda ketubatah, so what would be the
story by fruit attached to a tree? So says, well, שמואל Shmuel
already said, even if it's only a tree for its fruit, even
if maybe the fruit don't exist yet, but it's just the tree
for its fruit, that's counted as קרקע karka because the tree is
connected to the ground and a קנין kinyan in the tree is
like a קנין kinyan in קרקע, karka, even if it's not the
whole ownership of the tree. So certainly the same would be true
for the fruit itself. So that and she would lose her כתובה.
ketubah. That counts as קרקע. karka. So אמר ליה, amar lei, אימא
דאמר שמואל? eima d'amar Shmuel? So he said back, one minute, when
did שמואל Shmuel say? התם דאקני ליה בגופיה דארעא, hatam d'aknei lei
b'gufeih d'ara, if he owns the tree for the fruit, he actually
has a part of the land, I mean the tree which is
connected to the land. אבל הכא פירי הוא, aval hacha peirei hu,
but here it's just fruit. Meaning, now, if the tree is considered
land even though it's growing from land, the fruit is also land.
But it became clear that what he meant is the fruit isn't
attached to the tree and that's why I'm asking the question. So
אמר ליה, amar lei, so then he got it. He said, מטלטלי
קא אמרת? metaltlei ka amart? Oh, you're talking about chattel, something that's
not attached to the land? מטלטלי ודאי לא קא אמינא, metaltlei vadai
lo ka amina, I'm certainly not, you know, I never said anything
about
chattel. The משנה mishna said קרקע, karka, that he's dividing his land
in estate and that's considered, that's when we'll say that it's seen
like he's really divesting himself of his whole property and a little
piece of קרקע karka also because you know, you never know how
much a piece of land is worth, maybe that is a piece
of it. Anyway, that's considered that she's willing to make her peace
with that and accept that that's payment of her כתובה. ketubah. Okay.
ההוא דפלגינהו. hahu d'falginehu. So now another case. A certain said, תלתא
לברתא תלתא לברתא ותלתא לאיתתא. tulta l'bras tulta l'bras u-tulta l'ittas. A
third to my daughter, daughter one, a third to daughter two, and
a third to my wife. That's again classic example, should say אבדה
כתובתה. ivda ketubatah. Okay. שכיבא חד מבנתיה. shchiva chad mibnatay. One of
the daughters died before he did, even though he was let's say
even a שכיב מרע. shchiv meira. Alright. So then he, the third
that he had distributed, because he was giving this all out as
a gift, he now came in ownership of new property. What was
the new property he came in ownership of? It was the third
he had given to one of his daughters. So even though the
wife, now we're getting to the question which was the debate of
the רשב"ם Rashbam and the רי מגאש, Ri Migash, even if the
wife lost her כתובה, ketubah, was she forfeiting her liens and therefore
she would have a right but still the debt still existed and
she would have a right to collect it if new money came
into the estate? Or was she completely forfeiting the debt? And the
נפקא מינה nafka minah is this case, new money comes into the
estate. So סבר רב פפא למימר, savar Rav Pappa l'meimar, רב פפא
Rav Pappa thought to say, לא שקלה אלא תלתא, lo shakla ela
tulta, she gets a third that she got, she doesn't get any
rights to this additional stuff. You know, if the third, and if
there's כתובה ketubah money to be paid off beyond that third, tough
luck. You know, אבדה כתובתה. ivda ketubatah. אמר ליה רב כהנא, amar
lei Rav Kahana, רב כהנא Rav Kahana said on דף קל"ג עמוד
א', daf kuf lamed gimmel amud aleph, אילו הדר קני מי לא
שקלה? ilu hadar kani mi lo shakla? Wait, if the husband were
to get new property, she would have rights to it. She didn't
give up her debt. She waived the liens on the property that
was being given to the daughters. But she did not give up
the actual debt. So she has a right to collect if new
money comes into the estate. וכיון דאילו הדר קני שקלה, vekivan d'ilu
hadar kani shakla, and since she would get if new money came
into the estate, so השתא נמי שקלה. hashta nami shakla. So now
even though he's inheriting back from his daughter, or you know, that
is new money coming into the estate, she has not given up
her debt and she has rights to it. Okay, so it's clear
that רב כהנא Rav Kahana holds two things. Number one is she
does not give up the debt, she's only giving up, waiving the
liens on the property that is currently being distributed. She has rights
on new property that comes in. And he's also holding that even
though this is a reclaiming of property that he had before, technically
speaking, it's new property and she has rights to
it. What רב פפא Rav Pappa holds is not clear. רב פפא
Rav Pappa might have agreed in principle but felt this is not
seen as new property, or he might have held that no, like
the simple sense of the משנה, mishna, she really gave up the
entire debt. Okay, continuing on. ההוא דפלגינהו לנכסיה לאיתתיה ולבניה. hahu d'falginehu
l'nichsei l'ittatei u-lvanei.
So now we're continuing again with applications of this משנה. Mishna. There's
a certain person who divided his estate between his wife and his
son. He distributed it. שייר חד דיקלא. shayar chad dikla.
Now, the one, the one tree he did not distribute, right? He
gave ten million dollars
of the property to the son, he gave a little plot of
land to the wife which was considered payment, which would be considered
payment in the כתובה, Kesuvah, if the whole estate was given away,
but he didn't give away the whole estate. There was one palm
tree that was not given away. סבר רבינא למימר, savar Ravina lemeimar,
לית לה lais lah אלא חד דיקלא. ela chad dikla.
So she, all she gets is the piece of property that she
received, and but that's איבדה כתובתה, ibdah kesuvatah, okay, and maybe similar
to like what רב כהנא Rav Kahana said before, she also has
rights to, she still has a lien, so she can collect from
the one palm tree, but basically it's a case of איבדה כתובתה.
ibdah kesuvatah. Okay, or maybe you could read it that he's sort
of saying, let's treat it as if she got the piece of
property she got plus the palm tree, okay, and still איבדה כתובתה.
ibdah kesuvatah. She's left with a little piece of property plus the
palm tree, but basically applying the principle of מחלק נכסיו. machelek nechasav.
All right, so אמר ליה רב יימר amar lei Rav Yeimar לרבינא,
leRavina, אי לית לה, ei lais lah, חד דיקלא נמי לית לה.
chad dikla nami lais lah.
If she doesn't have
rights to her כתובה, Kesuvah, then she shouldn't have rights to this
one palm tree, meaning if it's
איבדה כתובתה, ibdah kesuvatah, then why are you saying she still has
rights to the palm tree, which is really basically a way of
pointing out
that we're not saying that she has lost her כתובה. Kesuvah. אלא
מיגו דנחתא לדיקלא נחתא נמי לכולהו נכסי. ela migo denachsa ledikla nachsa
nami lechulhu nichsei.
Because she has rights to the one
דקל, dekel, meaning why does she have rights to the one דקל?
dekel? What he's basically saying is is that if she really was
מוחלת mucheles her כתובה, Kesuvah, you wouldn't have conceded she has rights
to that one palm tree. Why are you conceding she has rights
to the one palm tree? Because you're saying it wasn't a case
of fully dividing the land. Well, if it wasn't a case of
fully divesting of the land because there was one palm tree left,
and because it wasn't a case of מחלק נכסיו על פיו, machelek
nechasav al piv, she retains the rights to that one palm tree.
So since she retains the rights to that one palm tree because
she wasn't מוחלת mucheles her כתובה, Kesuvah, so she wasn't מוחלת mucheles
any of her כתובה, Kesuvah, okay. אלא כיון דנחתא, מיגו דנחתא לדיקלא
נחתינן נמי לכולהו נכסי. ela keivan denachsa, migo denachsa ledikla nachsinan nami
lechulhu nichsei. Because she doesn't, so basically because she has, you're conceding
she hasn't divested herself, she hasn't been מוחלת mucheles and she does
still have her liens, so she really retains all of the liens.
It's a way of saying that this is not a case of
what do you call it, of מחלק נכסיו. machelek nechasav. Now, the
רשב"ם Rashbam says that the reason is that it's not מחלק נכסיו
machelek nechasav is because, similar to the גמרא Gemara before, like if
it's not everything is being distributed, the woman will say like, or
like the case when the guy was healthy, well, maybe he'll get
more property. So here, well, maybe that one palm tree is enough
for me to collect for, so I'm not yet being מוחלת. mucheles.
He tries to sort of situate it in her psychology, but I
would just say more simply, which is that then where do you
draw the line? If we're only going to say it when all
the property is distributed, all means all. Oh, one palm tree, that
doesn't count as all. How about two palm trees? How about ten
palm trees? Like what's the limit? So no, we're going to treat,
if we're going to say this הלכה, halacha, which is going to
actually obviously disadvantage the woman and it's pretty harsh, we're only going
to limit it to cases that clearly can be delineated. All means
all. So that's basically what the גמרא Gemara is saying here. Okay.
אמר רב הונא, amar Rav Huna,
שכיב מרע שכתב כל נכסיו לאחר. shachiv meira shekasav kol nechasav leacher.
Now we're done with the case of the wife losing her כתובה.
Kesuvah. We're back to a normal person in his deathbed distributing his
property. So he writes off all of his property to a person,
to somebody. רואין, ro'in, you assess it. אם ראוי ליורשו, im ra'uy
leyorsho, if this person is fit to inherit him, like he gives
it all to one son from amongst the other sons, now we're
re-evoking רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא. Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka. אם ראוי ליורשו,
im ra'uy leyorsho, נוטלן משום ירושה. notlan mishum yerusha. So if he
has sons ראובן שמעון לוי ויהודה Reuven Shimon Levi v'Yehuda and he
writes, or he gives off distributes on his deathbed or whatever, all
of his property to ראובן, Reuven, then it's considered a ירושה yerusha
to ראובן, Reuven, not a מתנת ירושה. matanat yerusha. ואם לאו, ve'im
lav, but if it was to somebody who was not an heir
who would normally inherit, if he were to die, so נוטלן משום
מתנה, notlan mishum matana, then you treat it as a gift. All
right, so what does that basically sound like? It sounds like you
can give it all to ראובן Reuven and you can like redistribute
between your heirs, which is the position of רבי יוחנן
בן ברוקא. Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka. So the basic point is even
if you use the language of like ירושה, yerusha, then it still
works as רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka says you
can redistribute amongst your heirs. So אמר ליה רב נחמן amar lei
Rav Nachman לרב הונא, leRav Huna, גנבא גנובי למה לך? ganva genuvay
lamma lach? Why do you have to go around stealing? Stealing these
teachings. Meaning, if you're telling, if you basically want to פוסק pasken
like רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא, Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka, why are you
dressing... something up as like it's your idea and here's your פסק,
psak, you're really stealing it from רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא? Rabbi Yochanan
ben Beroka? Or, you know, you might want to say what he's
really saying is, why are you going sneaking around? Are you trying
to hide the fact that you're פסקנין paskening like רבי יוחנן בן
ברוקא? Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka? Own it! Okay. So אי סבירא לך
כרבי יוחנן בן ברוקא, Ei sevira lach ke-Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka, if
you hold like רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka and
that's your point, אימא eima say הלכה כרבי יוחנן בן ברוקא, halacha
ke-Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka, that we rule like רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא.
Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka. דשמעתך כרבי יוחנן בן ברוקא הוא. De-shamatach ke-Rabbi
Yochanan ben Beroka hu. Okay. דאזל. De-azal. Because what you just ruled
is you're basically saying רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא, Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka,
that if you give it to one kid amongst the other kids
then that you can redistribute. So
דאזל. de-azal. So דילמא כי הא קאמרת. dilma ki ha kaamart. Maybe
what you're really trying to say is the following. Maybe you're not
just trying to tell us the הלכה halacha that if you're giving
it to one kid and it's among others it can work משום
ירושה. mishum yerusha. Maybe what you're trying to actually tell us is
that if it's unclear whether you meant a gift or ירושה, yerusha,
we'll interpret it as ירושה yerusha if it's possible, if it is
somebody that could be ראוי לירשה, rauy le-yirsha, which is pretty funny,
which sort of sounded like that's what he was saying. But okay.
But maybe this was a way of surfacing the fact that what
you're really first doing is saying רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan
ben Beroka and now you're telling an application of it in the
following way. All right, so let's take a look. אם ראוי לירשה.
Im rauy le-yirsha. Where were we, excuse me. כי
הא קאמרת. Ki ha kaamart. דההוא
דהוה קא שכיב. De-hahu de-hava ka shachiv. Because actually there was a
case, you know, I know,
you know, saying רב נחמן Rav Nachman is saying to רב הונא,
Rav Huna, I know you're really trying to tell over a practical
case that occurred. That there was a person who was dying ואמרו
ליה ve-amru lei and people said to him נכסי למאן? nichsai le-man?
Who should we give your property to? So דילמא לפלניא, dilma le-planya,
should we perhaps give it to so and so? ואמר להו אלא
למאן? ve-amar le-hu ella le-man? Who else?
Okay. ואמרת לן ve-amart lan and you, you know רב הונא, Rav
Huna, you said to us עלה, ala, אם ראוי לירשה נוטלו משום
ירושה ואם לאו נוטלו משום מתנה, im rauy le-yirsha notlo mishum yerusha
ve-im lav notlo mishum matana, that okay, so he said who else,
of course you're going to give it to ראובן. Reuven. And you
said to us, okay I want you to understand if this
ראובן Reuven is a ראוי לירשה, rauy le-yirsha, is an heir and
he's just giving it all to one heir, we're going to treat
that even though it wasn't clear, did you mean a gift or
did you mean ירושה? yerusha? Even though it was ambiguous in what
capacity he wanted ראובן Reuven to have it, but if ראובן Reuven
is an heir even though it's redistributing like רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא,
Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka, but if it's possible to read it as
ירושה yerusha we'll read it as ירושה. yerusha. If not we'll read
it as מתנה. matana. Again, that sort of sounded like the point
that was being made before. But this is just surfacing the idea.
First let's establish we go like רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan
ben Beroka and then within that if there's ambiguity how you mean
to give it, if it's possible to read it as ירושה yerusha
we'll read it as ירושה. yerusha. Which is interesting because you would
think that within רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא, Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka, you
know, if it's really redistributing the ירושה yerusha you're playing around with
the way the תורה Torah had it set up. And maybe we
should be inclined to read it as מתנה matana unless we're forced
to read it as ירושה. yerusha. But since רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא
Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka thinks that you have the right to do
it, okay, so then we're going to read it as that's what
you're doing.
All right. So maybe that's what you meant to say to us.
אמר ליה
אין הכי קאמינא. Amar lei in hachi ka-amina. Yes,
that's exactly my point, that if it's ambiguous but it's possible to
read it as ירושה yerusha we'll read it as ירושה. yerusha. And
now the גמרא Gemara asks what difference does it make? Either way
ראובן Reuven is getting it. So the גמרא Gemara says למאי הלכתא?
le-mai hilchata? For what הלכה halacha does it matter if whether he
has it in the capacity of ירושה yerusha or מתנה? matana? So,
you know, you could say maybe differences about if the שכיב מרע
shachiv mera recovers or doesn't recover, is it all, is it מקצת,
miktzat, whatever but that's going to be discussions we're going to get
to. But the גמרא Gemara actually is assuming let's say it actually
does get transferred to ראובן. Reuven. It's not a question of how
framing it as ירושה yerusha מתנה matana might, you know, what if
ראובן Reuven actually gets it, what difference does it make what capacity
it's in? So it says סבר רב אדא בר אהבה לקמיה דרבא
למימר אם ראוי לירשה אלמנה ניזונת מנכסיו ואם לאו אין אלמנה ניזונת
מנכסיו. Savar Rav Adda bar Ahava le-kammei de-Rava le-meimar im rauy le-yirsha
almanah nizonet mi-nichasav ve-im lav ein almanah nizonet mi-nichasav. Here's the difference.
If it's a ירושה yerusha then the הלכה halacha is going back
to the woman and the כתובה, ketubah, that the woman has the
right based on the כתובה ketubah rights to continue to be, until
she gets the lump sum of her כתובה, ketubah, she has the
right to be supported by the estate of the dead husband from
what the heirs inherit. But she cannot have liens on property that
was sold to other people when property was sold by the dead
husband before he died to other people she can collect the lump
sum payment like any creditor, but she cannot have the ongoing right
to be supported in terms of
room and board from property sold to others because there's no limit.
You don't know how much the total amount. It's not fair to
others. But she does have that right to get the room and
board ongoing from the money inherited by the heirs. So he said
here's the difference. If ראובן Reuven gets it as an heir, then
the widow has the right to be supported. supported by that estate.
If ראובן Reuven was not a son and doesn't get it as
an heir, were he only get it as a gift, then she
would not have the right to get from that estate because that's
money being transferred to outside to others. That's a, seems like a
very good explanation. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said back, רבא Rava
said back to him, מיגרע גרע? Migra gara? What, it's worse? השתא
בירושה דאורייתא Hashta biyerusha de'oraita אמרת מזוני תנינא מנכסיה, amart mezoni tanina
minechasei,
when somebody inherits it by a Torah ירושה, Yerusha, she has rights
to get supported by
it. במתנה דרבנן Bematana derabbanan לא כל שכן? lo kol sheken? Certainly
a rabbinic gift she would have those rights. Now, who the heck
knows if that's a קל וחומר? Kal vachomer? I mean, before we
talked about קולי כתובה שנינו כאן, Kulei kesubah shanu kan, who knows
whether that, you know, whether that's a logic? And if anything, why
is that a logic? We just explained the difference. The difference was
was that outside people, it's not fair to them that she gets
ongoing support. And also, if that's the הלכה Halacha that outside people
she doesn't get ongoing support, why do we say by a מתנה
דרבנן Matana derabbanan she does get ongoing support? So what the רשב"ם
Rashbam says is we don't mean any gift. We mean specifically a
מתנה דרבנן, Matana derabbanan, a rabbinic gift that is functioning like a
ירושה. Yerusha. If the guy, when he's, you know, just normally sells
or gifts property to others, the woman with her כתובה, Kesubah, the
wife does not have a lien to, I mean, for the lump
sum, but not to collect the ongoing room and support. But on
his deathbed when he's distributing his property and we allow that to
be effective, whether it, you know, that is a way that the
Rabbis use the mechanism of gift to basically create a redistribution of
the estate, to basically create a will. That's what the whole שכיב
מרע Shechiv mera case is like. So, and that's why, you know,
it takes effect when he dies, a minute before he dies, and
all of that. We're basically trying to make it a type of
a ירושה Yerusha without פסקנין paskening like רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi
Yochanan ben Broka about actually directly remanipulating the ירושה, Yerusha, or even
רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka would use that if
it was somebody that was not an heir. So since that is
a rabbinic type of a ירושה, Yerusha, right? It's a, it's functioning
in a similar way, then, and it's not a real normal קנין,
Kinyan, then we're going to not steal the woman, take, compromise the
woman's rights. The same way if he normally bequeathed it by dying,
she would have rights to be supported, then this deathbed thing, which
is an alternative path while he's dying of where the property's going
to go, she's not going to lose her rights there either. Okay,
that's a really fascinating
חידוש. Chidush. Alright, but that's his response. So then what difference does
it make back to this question, if somebody is going to get
it as ירושה Yerusha or as מתנה? Matana? So the גמרא Gemara
says like this, אלא אמר רבא, Ella amar Rava, so rather רבא
Rava said, כדשלח רב אחא בר אויא, Kedishlach Rav Acha bar Avya,
like רב אחא בר אויא Rav Acha bar Avya said. לדברי רבי
יוחנן בן ברוקא, Ledivrei Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka, according to רבי יוחנן
בן ברוקא, Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka, where you're
redistributing the property, redistributing, if somebody says נכסי לך ואחריך לפלוני, Nichsay
lach ve'acharecha liploni, my property is to you and after you, ראובן,
Reuven, you, ראובן, Reuven, and after you, ראובן, Reuven, it's going to
go to שמעון. Shimon. Okay, אם היה ראשון ראוי ליורשו, Im haya
rishon ra'ui leyorsho, if ראובן Reuven was a son, even though it
was excluding the other eleven sons, it went all to ראובן Reuven
because of רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא, Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka,
and then ראובן Reuven dies, אין לשני במקום ראשון כלום. Ein lashaini
bimkom rishon klum. So שמעון Shimon doesn't get it. Even though normally
if you said to two strangers, you know, non-heir, I'm giving all
my property to you, ראובן, Reuven, and afterwards שמעון, Shimon, that's the
הלכה, Halacha, ראובן Reuven dies, it goes to שמעון. Shimon. But if
ראובן Reuven is your son, then שמעון Shimon doesn't get it. Why
not?
שאין לשון מתנה ולשון ירושה, She'ein lashon matana uleshon yerusha, because you're
not giving it to ראובן Reuven as a gift, you're giving it
as a ירושה Yerusha because he is one of your heirs. Now
you could give it as a gift, but unless it's explicit as
a gift, that's been our point, anything that's unexplicit as a gift
is going to be treated to ראובן Reuven as a ירושה. Yerusha.
And since ראובן Reuven is getting it because he's one of your
heirs
as ירושה Yerusha according to רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא, Rabbi Yochanan ben
Broka, וירושה אין לה הפסק, Viyerusha ein lah hafsek, and if he
gets it as an inheritance, you can't take away money that I
got as an inheritance and say after I get it as an
inheritance, it goes somewhere else. If it's a gift, you could stipulate:
you get it for this period of time and then after your
life it's going to go somewhere else. But an heir is an
heir, and an heir gets it absolutely. So that's the difference. If
ראובן Reuven is an heir, ואחריך Ve'acharecha will not do anything. If
ראובן Reuven it's a מתנה, Matana, ואחריך Ve'acharecha will do something. Now,
it's a little, alright, whatever. So, אין לה הפסק. Ein lah hafsek.
אמר ליה רבא לרב נחמן, Amar lei Rava le-Rav Nachman, והא
אפסקא? Veha afseka? What do you mean ירושה Yerusha doesn't have interruption?
When you gave it, you said first to you, ראובן, Reuven, and
then שמעון. Shimon. So the גמרא Gemara says no, הוא סבר יש
לה הפסק, Hu savar yesh lah hafsek, when you were giving it,
you thought that you could interrupt it, ורחמנא אמר אין לה הפסק,
Verachmana amar ein lah hafsek, but the Torah says sorry, if you're
giving it to ראובן, Reuven, then it's, ראובן Reuven is an heir,
he gets it as ירושה, Yerusha, and therefore even if you wanted
to try to move it over to שמעון Shimon afterwards, that's not
going to help. Now the interesting thing is we're not going to
say that because you said that language of ואחריך Ve'acharecha proves you
meant it
as... So really now it's a big חידוש. Chiddush. If you say
רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka and then you say
I'm giving it all to ראובן Reuven and you don't make clear
מתנה Matana or ירושה, Yerusha, we're going to interpret it as ירושה.
Yerusha. We are biased to interpret it as ירושה Yerusha even though
you're redistributing the Torah's ירושה. Yerusha. And even if you say אחריך
Achareicha which will only be effective if you meant מתנה, Matana, we're
going to interpret it as ירושה Yerusha and say you're trying to
do that but it won't work because it's a ירושה. Yerusha. Okay,
let's just finish up to the משנה. Mishna. הוא דאמר ליה לחבריה
Hu de'amar lei lechavrei top of קל"ג עמוד ב, Kaf lamed gimmel
amud bet, somebody said to his friend, נכסי לך ואחריך לפלוני וראשון
ראוי ליורשו הוה, Nechasai lecha ve'achareicha leploni verishon ra'uy leyorsho hava, exactly
this case. First to you and then to the next person, and
the first person was an heir. שכיב וראשון, Shechiv verishon, so the
first guy died after the שכיב מרע Shechiv mera died. אתא שני
וכתבה, Ata sheini vekatva, so the second one came and said, okay,
now it's mine. שסבר רב עיליש קמיה דרבא למימר, Shesevar Rav Ilish
kammai deRava lemimar, so רב עיליש Rav Ilish was there in front
of רבא Rava and the case came to him and he said,
שני נמי שקיל, Sheini nami shakil, okay, let's give it to the
second person. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so רבא Rava said, דייני דחצצתא
הכי דייני, Dayani dechatzatzat hachin dayani,
judges of halving, this was the way H-A-L-V-I-N-G, this is the way
the רשב"ם Rashbam said it, that's how they deal. Everything they want
to be a nice compromise, they want everything to work out smoothly,
they don't really focus on the עיקר דין, Ikkar din, you know,
they're just trying to make שלום Shalom and פשרה. Peshara. So you
say, okay, he said first one and then second, first one died,
now give it to the second one. That's not the real הלכה.
Halacha. Okay, לאו היינו דשלח רב אחא בר אויא, Lav hainu deshalaach
Rav Acha bar Avya,
this is exactly the case that was, you know, that רב אחא
בר אויא Rav Acha bar Avya sent, which is that, you know,
since the first one was ראוי ליורשו, Ra'uy leyorsho, it's a ירושה
Yerusha and אחריך Achareicha isn't effective.
איכסיף, Ichsaf, so he got embarrassed. רב עיליש Rav Ilish was embarrassed
that he met, that he got this wrong. Maybe he thought that
since he said אחריך Achareicha he meant מתנה, Matana, who knows, but
that wasn't the ruling that apparently was the accepted ruling. So קרי
עליה, Kari aleih, so רבא Rava said about him, אני ה' בעתה
אחישנה. Ani Hashem be'itah achishena. He says, you know, because he was
embarrassed, oh my God, if רבא Rava hadn't been here I would
have made a terrible mistake. So רבא Rava says, don't feel bad.
הקדוש ברוך הוא Hakadosh Baruch Hu says, I and God, you know,
in its right time I will hasten the redemption. You wouldn't have
made the mistake. I, you know, God made sure that I was
here in order to correct you, so and don't feel, don't feel
bad about it, it all worked out just fine. Okay, so we
will end with that now.